Look at this one.
انظر إلى هذه
Quite transparent.
يبدو واضحا
Right?
هل هذا جيد
It's just an ordinary stone.
هذا مجرد حجر عادي
I'll show you the ropes.
دعني أريك
This is called golden silk jade.
هذا يدعى اليشم الذهبي
It's not expensive.
ليست غالية
Just one yuan per gram.
قطعة واحدة فقط
It'll take forever to make money.
إلى متى سنكسب جرام واحد؟
This is Aquamarine.
هذا يسمى باو هاي لان
It's worth half a year's salary of other jobs.
هذا يمكن مقاومة عملك في الخارج لمدة نصف عام
That's all?
القليل فقط
Yes.
نعم
Remember
انظر
how it looks and pick it up.
تذكري التقطها بعد قليل لا تنسيه
Give a newbie like me one.
أنتما الاثنان تقسمان لي واحدة   مبتدئة
No way.
هذا غير ممكن
I was introduced by a friend.
يوزاي قدمها
Share one with me.
لنلعب معًا
If it weren't for your friend,
لو لم يقدمك يو
I wouldn't have brought you here.
لما أحضرتك للعب
You won't get anywhere like this.
أنت لا تفعل أي شيء
What's the big deal?
ما الرائع في ذلك
Hello.
مرحبا
Tursenhan, come here.
تو سون تفضل
How are you?
هل كل شيء على ما يرام
Hello, Madam.
أهلا وسهلا يا زوجة القرابة
Have you given the candy? Sit.
هل أعطيت السكر اجلس
Come on, eat.
هيا تناولي
Someone got it.
لقد حصلت عليها
Who won the buzkashi game?
‫من حصل على الماعز‬
Must be Batay. He rides so well.
‫با تاي هو بارع في ركوب الخيل‬
Batay?
با تاي
Is Batay coming?
هل ستأتي با
Batay was here
جاءت با في وقت مبكر
in the morning.
جئت في الصباح
As a relative,
با تاي قريبة
he's busy helping out.
أنا مشغول جداً أريد المساعدة
Will the players outside
الناس في المنافسة بالخارج
come here for dinner?
سيأتي إلى هنا لتناول الطعام، صحيح؟
Yes, all of them.
نعم   كلنا هنا لتناول الطعام
Great photos.
الصور جيد جدا
Yes.
نعم
Look. Great photos. Nice clothes.
انظروا كم كان الصور جيدًا وملابس جيدة أيضًا
Hello.
مرحبا مرحبا
Hello, everyone.
مرحبا مرحبا مرحبا
Have you seen Batay?
هل رأيتم با تاي
Batay.
با تاي
Where's Batay?
أين ذهبت با
Hello.
مرحبا
Thank you.
شكرا
Slow down.
ببطء ببطء
Am I right, Uncle?
صحيح يا عمي
Wenxiu!
ون شيو
Why are you here? Let's go.
لماذا أنت هنا؟ لنذهب
Where to?
إلى أين؟
To see something nice.
سآخذك لرؤية شيء جيد
What are you looking at? Come!
ما الذي تنظر إليه؟ لنذهب
Hurry. Come on.
‫اذهب بسرعة ماذا تفعل
Come on, take a look.
‫بسرعة بسرعة ألق نظرة‬
Narabi.
‫نالا بي‬
Where's the bride?
أين ذهبت؟
Let me check.
‫العروس دعني ألقي نظرة‬
Narabi!
‫نالا بي‬
Where did she go?
أين ذهب؟
Nevermind. Let's look.
‫لا يهم  تعال وانظر‬
Come here.
تعال
It's just like mine.
مثلي
I rented mine from the county
عندما تزوجت
when I got married.
استأجرتها في المقاطعة
It's pretty.
جميلة
This is pretty.
هذا جميل
Is this the bride's hat?
هل هذه قبعة العروس
A high hat.
قبعة عالية
So nice.
جميلة جدا
Let me put it on for you.
دعني أرتديه لك
It's okay. Come on.
لا بأس لنذهب
There's a mirror. Go.
‫توجد المرآة هيا هيا
No one's here.
لا يوجد أحد
Hurry up.
بسرعة بسرعة
Beautiful.
جميلة
Like this.
هكذا
I'll get you this.
سأحضر لك هذا
Pin it on, yeah?
‫ضع البطاقة، أليس كذلك؟
When girls here get married,
عندما تزوجت الفتاة هنا
the dads
أبوهم
prepare a lot of
‫أعدوا لهم الكثير من الأشياء‬
nice stuff for them.
وأضعها هنا
What's this called?
ما اسم هذا
Is this a gem?
هل هذا حجر؟
Yes! Gem!
حجر
Look. All of these are gems.
انظر هذه كلها
Do you like it?
جميلة
Tursenhan!
تو سون نادر
Someone's here for you.
هناك شخص يبحث عنك
Over there.
هناك
Come here.
تعال بسرعة
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
It's a wedding.
حفل الزفاف
Learning the ropes.
تتعلم مقدما
Dream on.
انسي الأمر
It hasn't even begun taking shape.
ثمانية كلمات لا يوجد خط واحد
Begin taking shape?
ليس هناك أي شيء
Your Mandarin's good.
صينية جيدة
I'm so fluent now.
اللغة الصينية جيدة الآن
My buddy Wenxiu
صديقتي وين شيو
said it's good enough
قالت لغتي الصينية الآن
to run a rest-stop
سأفتح مطعم في المقاطعة
in the county.
ممكن
Rest-stop? You mean a restaurant?
أيها الحكم، المطعم
A restaurant?
المطعم؟
Yes.
نعم
Run a restaurant?
سنفتح المطعم
Aren't we getting married?
ألن نتزوج؟
Hush. Others will hear you.
لا تقل هناك شخص
You have to make my father-in-law
تزوج؟ أخبري أبي
agree.
لا يوافق
What should I say?
كيف أقول
My grandma, parents, and I
قالت جدتي أيضا قال والداي أيضا
have tried.
قلت أيضا
Should I get my motorcycle to try?
هل تريد من دراجتي أن تتحدث؟
Why don't you talk to him?
‫اذهب وتحدث أيضا‬
I did.
لقد قلت
Even my parents talked to him, but he said no,
قال والداي إنه لا يوافق
Embarrassing?
‫محرج‬
So embarrassing?
محرج جدا
Even a lad like me isn't embarrassed
أنا شاب مثلك
to be with you,
أنت تربي طفلتين
who has two kids.
لم أشعر بالخجل
They...
إنهم
Are you embarrassed to marry me?
هل أنت محرج جداً من الزواج مني؟
No.
لا
Why marry me then?
لماذا تتزوجين معي
That's not it.
أليس كذلك
Don't deny it.
ماذا؟
Listen, goodness.
أقول لك هذا مزعج
If I don't marry you,
إذا لم أتزوجك
I'll take my kids
سآخذ طفلتين
to work in a rest-stop in the county.
أنا أعمل في مطعم المقاطعة
No.
لا
Marriage's off. Happy?
لم نتزوج، هل أنت سعيد؟
The end.
ماذا تريد أن تقول
No.
لا
My Mandarin's brilliant. I understand it.
Tiếnة صينية جيدة يمكنني فهمها
I'll go to him now!
سأذهب إليه الآن
I'll kill myself if he disagrees!
إذا لم يوافق فسأموت له
Stop it.
توقف عن الكلام
Go away!
ابتعد
The bride is here. Bride!
العروس هنا العروس
Narabi, you're right.
‫نالا بي أنت على حق‬
Batay won.
با تاي فاز
Where's Batay?
أين با تاي
Uncle Yao took him away.
تم أخذها من قبل العم آ ليه
The elders are discussing the marriage
يأمل كبار السن باتاي الزواج من كولان
of Batay and Kulan.
والزواج
No wonder.
ما قلته
He was grinning from ear to ear.
كان يبتسم كثيراً
He followed Kulan
في أي مدرسة في كولان منذ صغره
to her school
كان يذهب إلى أي مدرسة
and to work in
كولان يعمل في المدينة
the county seat.
ذهب إلى البلدة للعمل أيضاً
Narabi, you know that too.
‫نالا بيي أنت تعرف أليس كذلك‬
Narabi.
‫نالا بي‬
Are you crying?
هل تبكين؟
Where's her family?
أين والدتها؟
It's fine.
لا بأس
It's good
نحن هنا
for the bride to cry at the wedding.
من الجيد أن تبكي العروس في حفل الزفاف
She can't bear to leave her parents.
الشخص الذي لا يريد تربيتها
She's filial.
إنه مطيع
Haisar!
هاسال
What's up?
ماذا حدث؟
Let's go. The ball's begun.
هيا بنا، لقد بدأ الحفلة
Kulan and Batay are singing a duet.
كولان والبا يغنون معاً
Okay.
حسناً
We're leaving.
‫سنذهب‬
Bye, Narabi.
‫نانا بيي سنذهب أولا‬
I...
أنا
My friend put it on me just now.
لقد جربت صديقي للتو
Are you the Han girl from the provision store?
‫أنت أنت الفتاة من متجر البقالة‬
How do you know?
كيف عرفت
Everyone in the ranch knows
الناس في المزرعة يعرفون
about the Han girl
قالت أن هناك فتاة من أسرة هان
good at writing.
تجيد الكتابة
Don't tell anyone, okay?
لا تخبر الآخرين
Okay.
حسنا
Thank you.
شكرا
They said Batay and her are a perfect match.
‫قالوا أن با والآخرين مناسبان جدا‬
I don't really see it.
لا أعتقد أنه مناسب بشكل خاص
Nice! Very nice!
جيد جيد جدا
Good.
حسنا
Kara jorga?
الحصان الأسود
Yes.
نعم
♫Tomarey♫
‫토مار
♫Hey, hey, Tomarey♫
مرحباً 토مار
♫Show me a glimpse of love♫
أظهر لي بعض الحب
♫My beloved Tomarey♫
토مار حبي
♫Tomarey♫
토مار
What does it mean?
ما معنى هذا؟
This song?
هل هذه الأغنية
It's about love.
إنه الحب
"I fell in love with a lad.
وقعت في حب شاب
What should I do?"
ماذا أفعل ماذا أفعل
♫My beloved Saule♫
عزيزي "شا وو لي"
♫I really wanna become your song♫
أريد أن أكون أغنيتك
Another love song?
لماذا هي أغنية حب مرة أخرى
Love this, love that.
لماذا نحب بعضنا البعض كل يوم
What does it mean?
ماذا يعني هذا؟
It means,
هذا يعني
"I like you.
أنا أحبك
If you don't like me,
إذا كنت لا تحبني
I'll die."
سأموت
Annoying!
مزعج مزعج مزعج
You're here too?
أنت هنا أيضا
Yes.
نعم
What dance was that?
ماذا ترقصين؟
Why weren't you dancing?
لماذا لم تأتي للرقص
Where have you been?
أين ذهبت؟
I went to lasso a horse.
ذهبت إلى حصان.
Why are you at a Tuoyi?
‫لماذا أتيت إلى حفلة راقص‬
Tokan brought me.
توكين أحضرتني إلى هنا
Just in time.
جيد
I have something big
لدي شيء مهم اليوم
to tell you.
لأخبرك
Let's go.
هيا
Can I not hear it?
هل يمكنني ألا أستمع
No, it's a big deal. Let's go.
يجب أن تستمع إلى الأمر الكبير لنذهب
I don't want to.
لا أريد أن أسمع
Where are we going?
إلى أين تذهب؟
You'll know when we're there.
ستعرفين عندما تذهبين
Snowshoe?
ركوب الثلج
Why did you bring it out?
لماذا أحضرته إلى هنا؟
For some fresh air.
أخرجه للتنفس
To adapt to crowded environments.
كي يتعاد على البيئة الكثيرة
Here.
تفضل
What's wrong, Baby?
ما الأمر يا حبيبتي
Do you want some, Baby?
هل تريدين أن تأكلي يا حبيبتي
Have a bite.
تناولي قضمة
Good job.
جيد جدا
Remember?
هل تتذكرين
Don't be scared.
لا أخاف
We made a promise.
ألم نتفق
Look, it's the girl I like.
انظري الفتاة التي أحبها
Don't embarrass me. Let me ride you.
إذا لم تسمح لي بالركب فسأشعر بالخجل
Well done.
رائع
Well done!
رائع رائع
Well done, Snowshoe!
‫ممتاز ركوب الثلج‬
Wow!
رائع
Snowshoe lets you ride it?
ركوب الثلج
Yes.
نعم
It's slowly recovering.
إنه يتحسن ببطء
You're amazing.
أنت رائع
What did you say to make it
ماذا قلت له للتو
listen to you?
إنه مطيع
It's a secret.
سر
Don't you have something to tell me?
أليس لديك شيء تريد إخباري به
Yes, it'll be Eid al-Adha soon.
نعم بعد فترة من عيد غول بانغ
It's an important festival,
عيد مهم جدا
you know?
هل تعرف
Just like
مثل
the New Year.
‫المهم مثل عيد الربيع‬
There will be a horse race meeting.
.سيكون هناك مسابقة الخيل
I'm taking Snowshoe to join
.سأحضر مسابقة رماية السهام
the archery competition.
للمشاركة في مسابقة رماية السهام
If it's fine then,
إذا في ذلك الوقت
it'll mean
لا توجد مشكلة
it's recovered.
هذا يثبت أنه شفي
Will you go?
هل ستذهبين
Is that it?
هذا هو الأمر
Yes.
نعم
Nothing else to tell me?
ألا يوجد شيء آخر تريد إخباري به؟
About what?
ما الأمر؟
I heard you're getting engaged to Kulan.
سمعت أنك ستتزوج من كولان
Uncle Yao talked to me.
قال لي عم آريه
Aren't you gonna tell me?
ألا تريد أن تخبرني
Is it necessary?
لا داعي
I'm not the one
حبيب كولان
Kulan likes.
ليس أنا
I don't like Kulan either.
كما أن حبيبي ليس كولان
Yes.
أجل
Who do you...
حبيبك
like?
من؟
Who I like?
حبيبي
Isn't it obvious?
أليس هذا واضحاً؟
How?
أين واضح
It's...
نعم
Look.
انظر
Who's the first to see Snowshoe's progress?
من رأى التقدم على الثلج لأول مرة؟
I showed it to you.
سأريك
Don't you get it?
ألم تفهم بعد؟
Not really.
لا أفهم
Why not?
لماذا لا تفهم
That's what it means!
هذا هو المعنى
Snowshoe!
ركوب الثلج
Come back!
عد
Come back, Snowshoe!
‫ارجع اركض الثلج‬
Snowshoe!
ركوب الثلج
You can't go there!
لا يمكنك الذهاب هناك
Wenxiu!
"ون سيو".
Batay, what kind of a friend are you?
با تاي هل أنت صديق جيد؟
You know I like Kulan, but you still want to marry her.
أنت تعرف أنني أحب كولان لكنك تريد الزواج منها
Is it not enough to beat me in buzkashi?
لقد هزمتني، هل تريد أن تأخذها؟
Marrying her?
هل ستتزوجها؟
Pull them apart!
اسحبوهم بسرعة
Are you bitter about losing to me in buzkashi?
لقد خسر الماعز، ألا تستسلم؟
Who wants to marry Kulan?
لا أريد الزواج من كولان
-Don't hit Batay's face. -You're marrying Kulan?
لا تضربي وجه با، سأتزوج من كولان
Batay, explain to them.
با تاي، اشرح لهم
Hurry, talk them out of it!
‫بسرعة إقناعهم
How dare you steal Mohebit's girl?
لماذا سرقت الفتاة التي لا مثيل لها؟
Brothers, attack!
أيها الإخوة اقتلوهم
No, you misunderstood!
لا   لقد أسأت الفهم
Admit defeat!
هل تستسلم؟
No!
لا تستسلم
Explain it!
اشرح بسرعة
Explain it to them!
أخبرهم بوضوح
Uncle Yao, explain to them
عمي آ ليه  اشرح لهم إنه سوء فهم
it's a mix-up!
أخبرهم بسرعة
I can't believe Dad.
يا أبي
Why didn't he ask me?
لماذا لم تسأل بوضوح
Mohebit's the one I'm dating.
الشخص الذي يحبني هو "موهي فاي فاي"
Mohebit really likes you.
ماو هيبري يحبك حقا
Look, he's still fighting.
انظر إليه، لا يزال يلعب
Come on. He just wants to win.
يكفي إنه يريد الفوز
He's bitter he lost to Batay
لقد هزمه في المسابقة
in buzkashi.
لم يستسلم أبدًا
Are you bitter about losing to me in buzkashi?
هل أنت غير مقتنع؟
Stop it, Batay.
توقف يا با تاي
Admit defeat!
هل تستسلم أم لا
No!
‫لا تستسلم‬
Batay!
با تاي
Gosh!
يا إلهي
Stop it!
توقف
Enough!
حسنا
That's enough.
حسناً، هذا يكفي
Kulan isn't marrying Batay.
كولان لم تتزوج من با تاي
It's a mix-up.
إنه سوء فهم
I think they're tired.
يبدو أنهم متعبون
Admit defeat!
هل تستسلم؟
Enough.
هذا يكفي
I'll love him forever.
أنا أحبه إلى الأبد
Let me kiss you.
تعال قبلي وجهي
No!
لا
Batay, buddy.
با تاي صديق
Wenxiu.
ون شيو
Kulan.
كولان
Let's go.
لنذهب
It's 3 a.m.
الساعة الثالثة
I have to milk the sheep at 5 a.m.
‫في الخامسة صباحاً يجب أن تضغط على اللبن
Let's go.
هيا
Let's go back.
.هيا بنا، هيا بنا
You're the only friend who beat me in a horse race.
أنت صديقي الوحيد الذي هزمني في مسابقة الخيل
He's a real man.
إنه رجل
He beat me in buzkashi.
هزمني في مباراة الماعز
Awesome.
إنه رائع
Batay.
با تاي
It's all in the wine.
كلها في النبيذ
Bye.
لنذهب
-We’re leaving. Bye. -Bye.
سنذهب -مع السلامة -
I'll go to your house next time.
سأذهب إلى منزلك في يوم آخر
Wenxiu.
ون شيو
W-Wenxiu.
"وين سيو".
Are you leaving?
هل ستغادر؟
We're going back to Naren.
سنعود إلى نارين
Naren?
ذلك رن
It's far.
لا يقترب من البشر
It'll take two hours on foot.
سنعود لمدة ساعتين
They have work to do in the day.
.لا يزال لديهم عمل في النهار
Do you know there's a horse race meeting soon?
.سيكون هناك مسابقة الخيل بعد فترة
I know.
أعرف
Won't everyone be there?
ألن يذهب الجميع إلى المنافسة؟
See you then.
.أراك لاحقاً
Okay.
حسنا
Bye.
مع السلامة
Wenxiu.
ون شيو
Who was that?
من؟
He came with friends.
هل أتيت مع الأصدقاء؟
They're Daurs.
قال إنه من عائلة "داكار"
He is Haisar's friend from Tacheng.
إنه صديق هاسال من تا تشينج
He works at the water plant.
‫يعمل في مصنع الماء
Wenxiu!
ون شيو
Wenxiu.
"ون سيو".
We grew up together,
لقد كبرنا معاً
riding horses.
ركوب الخيل معا
Grew up together.
كبرنا معا أليس كذلك
Right.
صحيح
My dad can't herd sheep today.
أبي لا يستطيع وضع الخروف اليوم
I have to do it.
يجب أن أضع الخروف
Yes.
نعم
Tokan.
توكين
Do you have any spare workbooks?
هل لديك دفتر واجبات إضافية في منزلك
Yerdana should have some.
يجب أن يكون هناك
Yerdana?
"ييدا"؟
He's eight years old,
إنه في الثامنة من عمره
but I've never seen him do homework.
لم أره يكتب الواجبات
Really.
حقا
What should I do?
ماذا يجب أن نفعل؟
I'm out of paper.
لقد انتهيت من استخدام الورق
I can't buy it on the ranch.
لا يمكن شرائها في المزرعة
Your family owns the only store around.
لكن منزلك هو المتجر الوحيد
Where can you buy it?
أين يمكنني شرائها
Oh no.
ما العمل
Wenxiu!
"ون سيو".
Grandpa, the quilt was upside down last night.
جدي، لقد عكس اللحاف ليلة أمس
This side's for your foot, not your head.
هذه القدم ليست الرأس
Really?
حقًا؟
Yes.
نعم
It's okay.
لا بأس
Don't tell your mom, okay?
لا تخبري والدتك
Okay.
حسنا
Child.
بني
Make tea after folding the quilt.
قومي بطهي اللحاف واطبخ الشاي
Okay.
حسنا
Nadyra, go make tea.
‫ناديلا اذهبي لتطبخ الشاي‬
I'll find you when I'm free.
سأذهب للبحث عنك
Bye.
مع السلامة
I've never been apart from
أنا ناديلا وليدا
Nadyra and Yerdana.
لم نفترق أبدا
Is Dad taking good care of them?
لا أعرف إن كان أبي يستطيع الاعتناء به
Close your mouth.
اخرس
I can see your tonsils.
لقد رأيت جسد الكرز
I didn't expect you to be
لم أتوقع
her daughter.
يأتي الأم وابنته
I didn't expect you to be lovers either.
لم أكن أتوقع أن يأتي زوجكما
It's the power of love.
قوة الحب
We've agreed we're free to love.
اتفقنا، حرية الحب
If you don't eat,
ما رأيك أن نأكل شيئا أولا
I won't dare to eat.
لا أجرؤ على تناول الطعام
It's delicious. Wild ones?
هذه لذيذة   البرية
Did you get it from the ranch?
هل أحضرته من المزرعة
Say something.
قل شيئا
Wild ones.
البرية
All picked from the ranch?
هل خلعت كل شيء من المزرعة
What else?
وإلا
From the mountain's pine forest.
قطفتها في الغابة
No wonder it tastes so different.
لذلك قلت إن مذاقها مختلف تمامًا
This is the green pollution-free food
الآن يقترح في المدينة أن يأكل
they're advocating
الطعام الأخضر بدون التلوث
in the city.
هذا كل شيء
Grandma, eat more. It's good for your lungs.
جدتي تناولي المزيد هذا جيد لرئتك
Then get some more.
اذهب واحضر المزيد
The locals don't eat this.
إنهم المحليون لا يأكلون هذا
Dry them
تجف
to sell at the county
مع الصابون الأسود
with the black herbal soap.
مع الصندوق الأسود
Sure.
حسنًا
I'll pick some after eating.
بعد أن أنتهي من الأكل سأذهب لأحضر القليل
Okay.
حسنا
But you don't know the way.
ألا تعرف الطريق
Eat quickly.
كلي بسرعة
Then lead the way.
أرشدني الطريق بعد الأكل
What's going on?
ماذا حدث؟
What's with him?
ماذا حدث له؟
Didn't you go out to buy sheep?
ألم تقل إنه سيذهب لشراء الخروف؟
Why did you bring a man back?
لماذا أحضرت رجلا
He's just a sheep.
أليست الخروف التي أحضرتها؟
Explain yourself.
أخبرني
On the way,
أليس مجرد شراء الخروف
I went further and further...
كلما ذهبت أبعد وأبعد
until I got to Gobi.
وذهبت إلى غوبي
So I went to Fairy Cove to see your dad.
لذا ذهبت إلى خليج الجنية لرؤية والدك
I found him on the way.
ثم التقطته في الطريق
Listen.
أقول لك
I feel like
أعتقد أن هذا الأمر
your dad's spirit
أنه في الظلام
made this happen.
في الظلام
You're blaming my dad?
أنت تلوم والدي
Let's set off!
لنذهب
I'm sleepy.
أشعر بالنعاس
I stayed up all night.
لم أنم طوال الليل
Where did you go that you didn't sleep?
لا يمكنك النوم في أي مكان تذهبين
It's hot. Drink more water.
اشرب المزيد من الماء في الجو حار
Go rest. I'll wash that later.
لا تغسلي   سأعود في المساء
It's okay.
لا بأس
Come out!
اخرج
Slow down. I have altitude sickness.
‫ببطء أنا أعلى قليلا‬
But it's just over 2,000 m.
ارتفاع ارتفاع ارتفاع أكثر من 2000
I'm serious. It's still high.
حقًا، إنه أعلى بكثير من ألفين
You look skinny,
تبدو نحيفة
but...
أنت
you're quite fit.
قوتك البدنية جيدة
Don't you think you've changed?
ألا تعتقد أنك تغيرت؟
Do you recall
هل تتذكرين
our chat on the rooftop?
ما تحدثنا عنه على السطح
You said you wanted to be a writer in Beijing.
قلت إنك ستذهب إلى بكين ككاتب
I said I'd work hard to get rich.
قلت أنني سأبذل قصارى جهدي للحصول على أموالي
Remember?
هل تذكرين
Money's all you know.
المال المال المال أنت فقط تعرف المال
How else can we get food?
كيف تأكل بدون المال
How else can we live?
كيف نعيش بدون المال
A good life requires money.
الحياة الجيدة تحتاج إلى المال لدعم
It depends.
هذا يعتمد على ما هو جيد
Some good lives don't cost much.
الحياة الجيدة لا تنفق الكثير من المال
So many.
كثير جدا
Can you cut them off?
هل تستطيع قطعه؟
Why not?
لماذا لا تستطيع قطعه
I quit high school and started working.
خرجت للعمل قبل التخرج من المدرسة الثانوية
I did everything.
لم أفعل أي شيء
Listen, whenever I see wood ear,
أقول لك بمجرد أن أرى آر الخشب
I wanna laugh.
أريد أن أضحك
My dad had gastric perforation from drinking.
كان أبي يعاني من ثغرات المعدة وشرب الخمر
We were poor back then.
في ذلك الوقت لم يكن هناك الكثير من المال في المنزل
We couldn't afford meat.
لم أستطع أكل اللحم
My mom bought it that day.
اشترت أمي ذلك اليوم
I recall it was
أتذكر خمسة يوان
five-yuan ribs.
خمس قطع من الأضلاع
With wood ear and ginseng,
مع ذلك الفطر الخشبي
she made soup
وعاء الحساء
to heal my dad's stomach.
‫وقال إنه سيغذي معدته
My sister and I took that jar.
أنا وأختي سنحمل هذا الكأس
We walked to the hospital.
ثم
I kept wondering
أشعر بغرابة
why it smelled so good.
لماذا رائحته طيبة جدا
I couldn't resist.
لم أتحمل
I drank it all outside the hospital.
تحت المستشفى
My sister started to bawl.
أختي في الطابق السفلي
She was scared.
أخاف
"Dad will kill us when he finds out!"
سيضرب أبي حتى الموت
So I looked around the hospital
سأبحث عن ذلك المستشفى
for the hot water kettle.
وضعت الماء الساخن وأحضر الزجاجة الساخنة
I added half a kettle
أضفت نصف علبة
and gave it to him.
ثم أحضرها له
When I left home at 18,
عندما خرج 17 8
he stopped me.
لم يسمح لي بالخروج
He said,
لا يسمح لي بالخروج
"If you dare leave,
قال إنه قال إذا تجرأت على المغادرة
come back only when you're successful."
إلا إذا نجحت
I haven't seen him for years.
لم أره منذ سنوات
I wanna earn a fortune
أريد أن أجني بعض المال خلال هذين العامين
to go back
سأعود
and throw the money at him.
سأرفض المال أمامه
And I'll tell him this,
أنا فقط أسأله
"I've made it.
لقد نجحت
Have you?"
هل نجحت؟
That'd feel great.
هكذا أشعر بالراحة
Cut them off yourself.
اقطعيه
I'll find a place to nap.
سأجد مكان للنوم
Be back in 40 minutes.
40 دقيقة ستعود
Get me a bottle of water later.
‫تعال وأحضر زجاجة ماء بعد قليل
There's a stream there.
هناك مياه نهر
And press this.
ثم ضغط على هذا
Let go.
اتركني
Go.
هيا
This is...
هذا
This...
هذا الشيء
Don't give up.
لا تستسلم
Didn't you fall when learning to ride horses?
ألم تتعلم ركوب الخيل من قبل؟
We are born to ride horses.
‫كنا نعرف كيف نركب الخيل منذ ولادتنا‬
Gosh.
هذا الشخص
You're exaggerating.
هذا مبالغ فيه
You'd still have fallen down at least once.
‫على أي حال سقوط مرتين‬
Is it nice?
هل أبدو جميلة
What's nice about a shard of glass?
الزجاج المكسور انظر إلى جمالك
My emerald.
حجري الأخضر
Hello.
مرحبا
-Hello.
مرحبا مرحبا
How's Nadyra?
كيف حال ناديلا
She's much better.
الآن أفضل بكثير
Her mom applied some ointment for her.
وضعت والدتها دواء الحرارة لها
Nadyra's still young.
ناديلا لا لا تزال صغيرة
I hope she doesn't get a scar.
أخشى أن يترك ندبة في يدي
Men are careless.
الرجال مهملون
How can you let a child make tea?
كيف يمكن أن يطبخ الأطفال الشاي
I didn't ask her to make tea.
لم أطلب منها أن تطبخ الشاي
I asked Yerdana, but he...
طلبت من ييدا أن يطبخه
Forget it. It's my fault in the end.
خلاص، إنه خطأي في النهاية
It's women's business to take care of children.
في الأصل رعاية الأطفال أمر النساء
Now it's women's business?
في هذا الوقت أصبح أمر النساء
Then why won't you let the kids follow Tokan?
لكنك لم تسمح لي أن أعتني بالطفل
Sulitan.
سو لي تان
What are you doing here?
ماذا تفعل هنا؟
I wasn't finished.
غادرت قبل أن تقول
I'm here to get some herbs for Nadyra's burn wound.
‫أنا هنا لأحضر بعض الأعشاب لأحرق ناديلا‬
We have it.
نعم نعم
Take a rest here. I'll get it.
استريحي هنا سأحضره
Okay.
حسنا
Sit over there.
‫اذهب هناك اجلس‬
Why's he here? To get soap?
ماذا يفعل هنا؟ أحضر الصابون
Sulitan.
أخي
Keep this.
خذها
It's you.
اتضح أنه أنت
I saved you,
أنقذتك
but you told Aybek?
لكنك أخبرت آيي بيك
What do you want?
ماذا تريد أن تفعل؟
Sulitan.
سو لي تان
Are you threatening me?
تريد تهديدي
Sulitan, stop.
سو لي تان حسنا
Sulitan, Fengxia didn't say anything.
سو لي تان تشانغ فنغ شيا لم يقل أي شيء
Then how did you know?
كيف عرفت
Look.
انظر
She secretly kept evidence
ترك الدليل سرا
to expose me.
تريد أن تكشف أمري
So you admit you're hiding a gun?
هل تعترف أنك تخفي مسدساً؟
How ungrateful!
ناكر للجميل
Enough.
حسنا حسنا
Sulitan.
سو لي تان
No one told me.
لم يخبرني أحد
When you didn't dare swear to it,
طلبت منك أن تعهد أنك لا تجرؤ في ذلك اليوم
I knew you must've hidden one.
كنت أعلم أنك تخفي شيئاً
Since you admit it,
بما أنك اعترفت
give it to me.
أعطها لي
I can go to your house to get it.
سأذهب إلى منزلك لأخذها
Sulitan!
سو لي تان
What's wrong with him?
ماذا تفعل
So stubborn.
عنيد جدا
Seriously.
حقا
She's a girl.
إنها فتاة
What if there's a scar on her face?
ماذا لو كان هناك ندبة على وجهها؟ انظر
You said you'd take good care of them.
ألم تقل أنك ستعتني بالطفل جيداً؟
Is this it?
هل تعتني بهذا الشكل
You wouldn't let me take my kids with me.
قلت إنني آخذ الطفل، لكنك لا توافق
Don't you care about them?
أنت لا تهتم بالطفل
Of course I do.
كيف لا أشعر بالأسف
You think what you do is for everyone's sake.
هل تعتقد أنك تفعل الخير للجميع
You must keep the kids.
وطلب مني أن أترك الطفل
Batay must herd.
‫وطلب من با تاي أن تتركها‬
Batay doesn't even dare confess to the girl he likes.
لا تجرؤ با على الاعتراف بحب الفتاة التي تحبها
I didn't stop Batay from finding a partner.
لم أوقف السيدة با في البحث عن حبيب
That's because he likes the girl from the store.
إنه يحب الفتاة في متجر البقالة
Will you agree to it?
هل توافقين؟
No!
لا
No.
لا يمكن
♫Moonlight swaying on the ground♫
ضوء القمر يهز على الأرض
♫Blurry light begins to surround me♫
بدأ ضوء غامض حولك
Dad!
أبي
Are you dating the girl from the store?
هل وقعت في الحب مع فتاة في متجر البقالة
Listen.
أقول لك
You can marry anyone but her.
لا أحد يستطيع الزواج منها
Will she herd with you?
هل ستطلق الرعاية معك؟
Will she wash, cook, and care for your family?
هل يمكنها أن تغسل ملابسك وتطبخ المنزل
She'll go back to the city
سيكون الأمر مثل توكين
like Tokan!
ستعود إلى المدينة
I'm not staying in the ranch.
لن أبقى في المزرعة
I told you
لقد قلت من قبل
I'm returning to the stable.
سأعود إلى ساحة الخيل
You...
...أنت
Let's see how...
أريد أن أرى
Dad!
أبي
You only care about that horse.
.هذا الخيل الوحيد في عينيك
I sent you to raise horses.
طلبت منك أن تربي الخيول
Snowshoe!
‫ركوب الثلج‬
But you only care about that horse.
.هذا الخيل الوحيد في عينيك
I sent you to raise horses.
.طلبت منك تربية الخيول
Bastard.
أيها الوغد
Dad.
أبي
I'll go herd the sheep.
سأذهب لإطلاق الخروف